Finding Aid for Gerald L. K. Smith Papers 1922-1976
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Administrative files
  The collection includes a body of records, labeled for convenience Administrative Files. Preserved in fragments for the years between 1948 and the early 1970s, this series details the day-to-day operation of the Smith office. Much of the correspondence in this file was addressed to the Christian Nationalist Crusade, and the replies are either form responses from Smith or from his office manager, Opal Tanner White. The importance of the file is its documentation of the kind of support which Smith received. Some of the letters are responses to Smith's appeals for funds or free literature. Some concern problems with subscriptions to the Cross and the Flag; while others come from people concerned about current events or with information to offer about the state of the world.
  - 1948-1952 1958-November 1959 (Box 82)
  - November 1959-March 1960 (Box 83)
  - March-May 1960 (Box 84)
  - June-August 1960 (Box 85)
  - August-November 1960 (Box 86)
  - November 1960-1962 (Box 87)
  - 1963-June 1968 (Box 88)
  - July 1968-February 1969 (Box 89)
  - September 1969-October 1970 (Box 90)
- Loan file
  The Loan file (kept separate by Smith) consists of correspondence with individuals who had made loans of money to Smith or the CNC. The file is dated from 1969 to 1974.
  - 1969-1974 (Box 91)
- Christian Nationalist Crusade
  The Christian Nationalist Crusade series includes a collection of the newsletters published by Smith's organization since 1972 (copies of these also exist in the chronological series). The newsletters are arranged both by date and by topic.
  - Newsletters
    (by date)
    - 1972 (Box 92)
      - May-September (Box 92)
      - October-December (Box 92)
    - 1973
      - January-February (Box 92)
      - May (Box 92)
      - June-July (Box 92)
      - August-September (Box 92)
      - October-November (Box 92)
      - December (Box 92)
    - 1974
      - January-March (Box 92)
      - April-July (Box 92)
      - August-October (Box 92)
      - November (Box 92)
      - December (Box 92)
    - 1975
      - January-February (Box 92)
      - March-April (Box 92)
      - May (Box 92)
      - June-September (Box 92)
      - October-December (Box 92)
    - 1976
      - January-April (Box 92)
      - May-December (Box 92)
    - 1977
      - January-June (Box 92)
      - July-December (Box 92)
  - Newsletters (arranged topically)
    [Note: These are duplicates of materials in chronological series]
    - Agnew, Spriro T. (Box 92)
    - Blacks, 2 folders (Box 92)
    - Calley, Lt. William (Box 92)
    - China (Box 92)
    - Demonstrations (Box 92)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight (Box 92)
    - Energy crisis (Box 92)
    - Eureka Springs, Ark., 2 folders (Box 92)
    - Fluoridation (Box 92)
    - Hammer, Armand (Box 92)
    - Israel, 4 folders (Box 92)
    - Jews, 5 folders (Box 92)
    - Kennedy, John F. (Box 92)
    - Kennedy, John, assassination (Box 92)
    - Kennedy, Theodore (Box 92)
    - Kent, Tyler (Box 92)
    - King, Martin Luther (Box 92)
    - Kissinger, Henry (Box 92)
    - Literature lists (Box 92)
    - Long, Huey (Box 92)
    - MacArthur, Douglas (Box 92)
    - McCarthy, Joseph (Box 92)
    - Nixon, Richard (Box 92)
    - Pornography and sex education (Box 93)
    - Reuther, Walter (Box 93)
    - Smith, Gerald, personal experiences (Box 93)
    - Soviet Union (Box 93)
    - Supreme Court (Box 93)
    - United Nations (Box 93)
    - Wallace, George (Box 93)
    - Watergate (Box 93)
    - Miscellaneous, 14 folders (Box 93)
- Oral history/Microfilm project (and other MHC collected materials)
  The Oral history/Microfilm project series consists of materials collected or accumulated by the Michigan Historical Collections prior to the accessioning of the bulk of the Smith papers in 1982. Included is the transcript to the interview made with Gerald L. K. Smith in 1968 by staff members of the library, also correspondence between Smith and the MHC, and collected materials about Smith and his organization. A portion of this series consists of the microfilm of selections of the Smith papers made in the early 1970s. This microfilm was made at Smith's office in Los Angeles. The originals of these films subsequently came to the library in 1982.
  - Reports on visits with Smith by J. Fraser Cocks, III September 1967; and Robert M. Warner, June 1969 (Box 94)
  - Transcript of interview with Gerald L. K. Smith March 1968 Mar., 4 folders (Box 94)
  - Sound recording of interviews, 6 reels (Box 94)
  - Correspondence primarily with the Michigan Historical Collections, 2 folders (Box 94)
  - Books and articles about GLKS (largely critical) (Box 94)
  - Michigan Historical Collections vertical file on GLKS (Box 94)
  - Collected books and pamphlets published or distributed by the Christian Nationalist Crusade (Box 95)
  - Microfilm of Smith collection (Box 96)
    (selective only)
- L. Z. Smith
  (including material about GLKS)
  A small series of personal items of Smith's father, L. Z. Smith (principally clippings, notices of meetings, and a scattering of correspondence) has value for documentation of Smith's background.
  - Correspondence (Box 96)
  - Pocket diaries and notebooks (Box 97)
  - Clippings, 3 folders (Box 97)
  - Church miscellanea, 4 folders (Box 97)
- United Farmers of America (Opal Tanner)
  The Smith collection also includes a group of files relating to Opal Tanner's work as secretary of the United Farmers of America. Tanner (later Opal Tanner White) was with this organization at the time of her first involvement with Smith, and this no doubt explains why the records of UFA are now part of the Smith collection. The UFA records are of interest because it was a politically conservative organization whose head was supportive of some of the same causes as Smith.
  - Topical files circa 1944-1947
    - Avery, Hazelton (Box 97)
    - Binegar, H. W., 2 folders (Box 97)
    - Booth, A. H. (Box 97)
    - Norris, Ruth (Box 97)
    - Smith, Oscar B. (Box 97)
  - State files
    - Arizona (Box 97)
    - Georgia (Box 97)
    - Illinois, 2 folders (Box 97)
    - Indiana, 2 folders (Box 98)
    - Iowa (Box 98)
    - Kansas (Box 98)
    - Kentucky (Box 98)
    - Massachusetts (Box 98)
    - Minnesota (Box 98)
    - Montana (Box 98)
    - Nebraska (Box 98)
    - New Jersey (Box 98)
    - Ohio, 3 folders (Box 98)
    - Oklahoma (Box 98)
    - Pennsylvania (Box 98)
    - South Dakota (Box 98)
    - Texas (Box 98)
    - Wisconsin (Box 98)
    - Miscellaneous, 7 folders (Box 98)
    - Newspaper clipping re Carl H. Mote (Box 98)
- Newsletters, pamphlets, and flyers
  Preserved with the Smith papers are an accumulation of Newsletters and pamphlets of other right-wing organizations and individuals.
  - Published materials of other conservative individuals and groups (Box 99)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  The final series in the collection - Visual Materials - consist of Photographs, Motion Pictures, and Sound Recordings. The contents of these series are fully described in the container listing (boxes 100-102)
  - Photographs
    The Photographs subseries includes portraits of Smith and his wife, Elna Smith; photographs of meetings and conventions of the America First Party, of picketing and other political activity in support of Smith and his platform, and of Smith's associates and supporters; also photographs and portraits of celebrities, buildings, and activities, which Smith collected, probably for use in his publication The Cross and the Flag.
    - Portraits of Smith and his wife Elna (Box 100)
    - Snapshots and other informal photographs of Smith, his wife, and their friends (Box 100)
    - Activities of Smith
      - Committee of 1,000,000 (Box 100)
        (cartoon)
      - America First Party 1944 (Box 100)
      - Revival Meeting, Los Angeles 1945 (Box 100)
      - Audiences and demonstrations at America First/CNC meetings (Box 100)
      - Speakers (Box 100)
    - Associates and colleagues of G. L. K. Smith, 2 folders (Box 100)
    - Eureka Springs, Arkansas - Passion Play (Box 100)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 100)
    - Cross and the Flag (Box 100)
      (photographs for use in Smith's publications, or collected by him for other purposes)
    - Atomic Energy Commission (Box 100)
    - Blacks. (Box 100)
      (See also Military)
    - Communism (Box 100)
    - Conductors, orchestral (Box 100)
    - Faubus, Orville (Box 100)
    - Hollywood, California - Actors, artists (Box 100)
    - Individuals, identified (Box 100)
    - Individuals, unidentified (Box 100)
    - Israel (atrocities by Jews in Jordan, 1948 (Box 100)
    - Jews (Box 100)
    - Liberty Bell (making a replica) (Box 100)
    - Military (Box 100)
      (WWI, WWII, Korea; mainly of Blacks)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 100)
    - Politics and Politicians (Box 100)
    - Race Riots (Box 100)
  - Motion Pictures
    The motion pictures subseries consists of films collected by Smith. The films, some produced by the National Education Program, promote the conservative, anti-communist views espoused by Smith.
    - American Adventure Series: American Citizenship Education, 16mm, black and white, sound (Box 101)
      (Dr. Clifton L. Ganus, Jr., Commentator. Produced by the National Education Program.)
      - America's Distribution of Wealth, No. 8 (Box 101)
        [#1]
      - A Story of Enterprise, No. 9 (Box 101)
        [#2]
      - The Secret of American Production, No. 10 (Box 101)
        [#3]
      - The Profit System: Why Kill the Goose?, No 11 (Box 101)
        [#4]
      - The Responsibility of American Citizenship, No. 13 (Box 101)
        [#5]
    - My Latvia., 16mm, black and white, sound (Box 101)
      (Film footage shot by Albert Jeske, former manager of Latvian film production.) [#6]
    - The Two Berlins, 16mm, color, sound (Box 101)
      (Produced by the National Education Program) [#7]
    - Communist Encirclement, 1961, 16mm, color, sound (Box 101)
      (Produced by the National Education Program. Text by Glenn Green.) [#8]
    - Communism in Action, 16mm, color, sound (Box 102)
      (Produced by the National Education Program.)
      - Part 1: Communism's source and growth (Box 102)
        [#9]
      - Part 2: Life behind the Iron Curtain (Box 102)
        [#10]
    - Kuneitra - Death of a City, 16mm, color, sound (Box 102)
      (Concerning the destruction of a Syrian village in the Golan Heights by Israeli forces) [#11]
    - Hell in the City of Angels, 16mm, black and white, sound (Box 102)
      (Concerning racial rioting in Los Angeles, California.) [#12]
    - Operation Abolition: The Story of Communism in Action, 1960, 16mm, black and white, sound
      (Concerning the activities of the House Committee on UnAmerican Activities in San Francisco, California, May 12-14, 1960)
      - Complete version, 45 minutes (Box 102)
        [#13] [Location: Y-376-C]
      - TV Version, 28 minutes (Box 102)
        [#14]
  - Sound recordings: phonorecord discs, 33-1/3 RPM
    - Disc 1 (Box 1)
      - "Nationalism is Patriotism" by Douglas MacArthur
      - "This is Christian Nationalism" by Gerald L. K. Smith
    - Disc 2 (Box 2)
      - "The Plot to Undermine the Republic" by Gerald L. K. Smith
        (2 sides)